Alan Feder

https://www.alanfeder.com

11402 Gainsborough Road, Rockville, MD 20854

alanfeder@gmail.com (347) 625-9709

Summary

I am an experienced machine learning engineer with over ten years of expertise in harnessing artificial intelligence, machine learning, and data science to drive value. I have led projects developing models using both supervised and unsupervised methods, including generative AI, natural language processing techniques, and structured predictive ML models.

I am looking to help businesses and government utilize AI/ML and data science methods to solve their needs.

TECHNICAL SKILLS

- Languages & Tools: Python, R, SQL, git, bash, AWS (S3, EC2, Athena), Airflow, markdown, quarto
- Packages: Hugging Face, ollama, spacy, openai, scikit-learn, xgboost, statsmodels, streamlit, pandas
- AI/ML Methods: LLMs, RAG, BERT, prompt engineering, xgboost, LASSO, GLM, GAM, word2vec

Experience

Alan Feder Consulting

January 2023 - present

- Founder
 - Developed a knowledge base RAG-powered chatbot for a cybersecurity company, built on an AWS EC2 instance, utilizing the open-source AI models *Mistral-7B* and sentence-transformers
 - Created a predictive model for identifying asset types in a cybersecurity context, leveraging advanced AI techniques
 - Extracted and processed raw text, tables, and charts from financial documents to support private equity market research, using GPT-4V, unstructured.io, and other AI methods
 - Implemented an AI-based solution for matching group names from disparate lists using embedding models and semantic similarity measures

Johnson & Johnson (contract)

March 2024 - May 2024

- AI Technical Consultant
 - Designed and implemented an AI system that automatically converts protocols from oncology clinical trials into Case Report Forms
 - * Led to significant time and cost savings of over a month and \$60,000 per clinical trial

Invesco

September 2018 - September 2023

- Senior Principal Data Scientist
 - Created an LLM-powered tool analyzing public comments on proposed government regulations
 - * Using GPT 4, classified stakeholder sentiment, pinpointing support or opposition
 - * Using GPT 4 combined with RegEx, grouped and synthesized arguments, identifying key themes and measuring consensus
 - Enhanced internal chatbot by enabling summarization and comparison of related PDF documents
 - * Utilized retrieval-augmented generation (RAG) through LangChain and Qdrant vector databases
 - Devised a real estate-specific NLP-based sentiment signal to forecast index prices across real estate sub-sectors
 - * Detected sector-wide price fluctuations 5 months ahead of market data recognition
 - * Explicitly included expert real estate knowledge by working with industry leaders to develop bespoke sentiment dictionaries and tune NLP parameters

- * Developed streamlit web app which allowed research team to explore the model and run their own backtesting
- o Organized initiatives for internal Citizen Data Scientist program
 - * Oversaw capstone projects including the development of a new internal document search tool and cloud cost forecasting, leading to 20% increase in forecast accuracy
 - * Taught 12 investment professionals & 15 tech professionals lessons about machine learning
- **Developed an ensemble predictive model** for multifamily residential real estate, using geospatial and machine learning programming tools
 - * Predicted which neighborhoods will increase in rent, outperforming the benchmark by 8%
- Fine-tuned neural network (distilBERT) using Huggingface to classify the appropriateness of a news article for an internal ESG tool, achieving 92% accuracy and a 0.94 AUC

AIG Science

July 2014 - September 2018

- Data Scientist, Senior Manager
 - o Managed a team of three junior data scientists and one junior business analyst.
 - Enhanced workers' compensation claims forecasting boosting the accuracy of cash flow projections by 50%
 - Streamlined travel insurance claims handling
 - * Improved throughput by 30% by deploying a gradient boosting model (GBM), pre-approving low-risk claims

Swiss Re America

Pricing Actuary

Associate Risk Management Analyst

February 2012 - June 2014 June 2010 - February 2012

- Utilized Poisson regression to innovate the pricing of mid-sized casualty commercial risk insurance policies
- Built a mathematical model to calculate basis risk in parametric insurance contracts for hurricane risks based on historical data
 - * Incorporated geographic and time series data into models, comparing the payout from a hypothetical parametric structure to actual property insurance payouts
- Analyzed basis risk for extreme mortality bonds

EDUCATION

Graduate School of Arts & Sciences, Columbia University

May 2010

Master of Science in Statistics

New York, NY

Columbia College, Columbia University

Bachelor of Arts - Major: Mathematics, Concentration: Economics

May 2009 New York, NY

TEACHING, PRESENTATIONS, PUBLICATIONS, AND COMPETITIONS

- NYR Conference: RAGtime in the Big Apple: Chat with a Decade of NYR Talks, May 2024
- Bethesda Data Science Meetup: RAGs to Richer Answers: Using ChatGPT to Query Documents & Limit Hallucinations, Nov 2023
- University of Baltimore, Merrick School of Business: Adjunct Professor, Fall 2023 OPRE 605, Business Analytics
- Risk and Reward: Elizabeth Cohen, Alan Feder, et. al. "Stocks move on surprises: Using sentiment information for active portfolio management." vol. Q 3 2022, Invesco, 14 Oct. 2022, pp. 21-25.
- Data Science Salon: NLP in Finance: Beyond Predicting Alpha, March 2022
- Data Science Salon : Machine Learning Interpretability: How to Understand what your ML Model is Doing, Feb 2021
- Kaggle: 4th Place (out of 5,156) Porto Seguro's Safe Driver Prediction, Nov 2017